Robert Delford Brown
Archives of American Art, Smithsonian Institution
Robert Delford Brown papers
1964-2009
Archives of American Art, Smithsonian Institution
Brown, Robert Delford
3.7 linear feet
The papers of painter, sculptor, and performance artist Robert Delford Brown measure 3.7 linear feet and date from 1964-2009. The papers document his career as an artist and in particular the arts space "church" he founded in New York City, known as The First National Church of Exquisite Panic, Inc. The collection consists of biographical material, correspondence, church records, printed material, photographic material, and video records of performance art. Brown's early career is documented in one scrapbook containing photographs, notes, and press materials.
Provenance
Donated in 2010 by Lynda Roscoe Hartigan who purchased the collection at auction.
Restrictions on Access
Use of original papers requires an appointment. Use of archival audiovisual recordings with no duplicate access copy requires advance notice.
Biographical Note
Robert Delford Brown (1930-2009) was a painter, sculptor, and performance artist practicing in New York City, N.Y. Brown was a participant in many art happenings in New York during the 1960s and frequently performed in the persona of a religious leader and founder of his own religion and church, The First National Church of the Exquisite Panic, Inc. which functioned as a community arts space.
Brown was born in Portland, Colorado. His family later moved to Long Beach, California, and he recived bachelor's and master's degrees at University of California, Los Angeles. He began his career as a Surrealist and Abstract Expressionist painter, and in 1959 moved to New York City. In 1963 he married Rhett Cone. While visiting Paris he met the artist Allan Kaprow who encouraged him to participate in a 1964 performance of Karlheinz Stockhausen's "Originale." This performance served as the inspiration for founding The First National Church of Exquisite Panic, Inc. That same year Brown also gained media attention for his "Meat Show," an installation of raw meat which he created in a refrigerated room at the Washington Meat Market in New York City.
In 1967 Brown selected a former New York City branch library as a home for his church and hired Modernist architect Paul Rudolph to redesign the interior. He called the space "The Great Building Crack-Up" and lived there until 1997, hosting art exhibitions, happenings, and preaching his philosophy known as Pharblongence. During Brown's later career he organized many participatory art events, such as "Collaborative Action Gluings." He moved to Houston, Texas in 1997 and later moved to Wilmington, North Carolina, in preparation for a solo exhibition at the Cameron Art Museum in 2008. Robert Delford Brown died in 2009.
Scope and Content Note
The papers of painter, sculptor, and performance artist Robert Delford Brown measure 3.7 linear feet and date from 1964-2009. The papers document his career as an artist and in particular the arts space "church" he founded in New York City, known as The First National Church of Exquisite Panic, Inc. The collection consists of biographical material, correspondence, church records, printed material, photographic material, and video records of performance art. Brown's early career is documented in one scrapbook containing photographs, notes, and press materials.
Biographical material includes a career summary, one diary, one interview transcript, and two interview recordings on videocassette. Correspondence is minimal and includes four letters written by Brown and letters and postcards from others. Printed material consists mostly of books and event announcements documenting Brown's career. Photographs depict his travels in Brazil and China, artwork, and a collaborative event in Paris. Video recordings depict a solo performance art piece and three collaborative performance art events.
Records of the First National Church of Exquisite Panic, Inc. include items produced for events, such as graphics, a t-shirt, "teachings," as well as reproductions of artwork created as part of the church. Also included are founding documents and manifestos.
One scrapbook contains detailed documentation on Brown's career from 1964 to 1974. Included are photographs and press materials for his "Meat Show" event, additional records of the founding of his church, and photographs of various events and happenings at his church. People depicted in the photographs include Brown, Claes Oldenburg, and art critic Mario Amaya, among others.
Arrangement
The collection is arranged as 7 series:
Series 1: Biographical Material, 1992-2009 (Box 1, 5; 0.7 linear feet)
Series 2: Correspondence, 1970-2009 (Box 1; 4 folders)
Series 3: First National Church of Exquisite Panic, Inc. Records, 1968-2000s (Box 1, 4, 5; 0.7 linear feet)
Series 4: Printed Material, 1964-2008 (Box 1-2; 0.4 linear feet)
Series 5: Photographic Material, 1965-2009 (Box 2-3; 1.1 linear feet)
Series 6: Video Recordings of Performance Art, 1994-2005 (Box 3; 0.4 linear feet)
Series 7: Scrapbook, 1964-1974 (Box 5; 4 folders)
Names and Subject Terms
This collection is indexed in the online catalog of the Archives of American Art under the following terms:
Subjects:
Amaya, Mario; Oldenburg, Claes, 1929- --Photographs
Subjects-Topical:
Painters--New York (State)--New York; Performance artists--New York (State)--New York; Sculptors--New York (State)--New York
Types of Materials:
Diaries; Interviews; Photographs; Scrapbooks; Transcripts; VHS (videotape format); Video recordings
Series Descriptions/Container Listing
- Biographical Material, 1992-2009, Series 1:; (Box 1, 5; 0.7 linear feet)
  Found here are interviews with Robert Delford Brown and a small amount of biographical documentation. Included are a biographical summary which consists of a brief chronology, list of performances, exhibitions, and publications regarding Brown; one diary containing brief daily entries and illustrations; and notes regarding his life written on large sheets of paper. Also found is a transcript of an interview conducted by Robert C. Morgan; videocassette recordings of an interview conducted by Francesco Conz in Verona, Italy; and recordings of an interview, "I'm a Sweet Old Man Now," conducted by Mark Bloch for Panscan TV.
  - Biographical Summary, circa 1997 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Diary, 1992 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Essay, "The Strange Case of Robert Delford Brown (a.k.a. Saint Kittenish), Iconoclast-Part II," by Robert C. Morgan, circa 2004 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Interview Transcript, 2003 April 8 (Box 1, Folder 4-5)
  - "Conz Interview," Edited Master, 2002, (1 original videocassette: Betacam, 3 duplicate videocassettes: VHS) (Box 1, Folder 6-8)
  - "Conz Interview," Unedited Footage, 2002, (1 videocassette: Betacam) (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - "I'm a Sweet Old Man Now: A Visit with Robert Delford Brown at the Great Building Crackup", 1997, (1 original videocassette: VHS, 1 duplicate videocassette: VHS, 1 duplicate DVD) (Box 1, Folder 10-11)
  - Obituary, 2009 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Project Proposal, 2000s (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Notes, 2003 December 16 (Box 5, Folder 1)
- Correspondence, 1970-2009, Series 2:; (Box 1; 4 folders)
  Correspondence consists of four letters written by Robert Delford Brown, letters to Brown from art dealer Eugenia Butler, and a series of postcards from artist Victoria Schultz. Also found are digital scans and printed copies of illustrated letters from friend and fellow artist H. C. Westermann.
  - Letters Written by Robert Delford Brown, circa 2004-2008 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Letters from Eugenia Butler, 1970-1971 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Letters from H. C. Westermann (Digital Copies), 1970-1971, 2009 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Postcards from Victoria Schultz, 2002 (Box 1, Folder 17)
- First National Church of Exquisite Panic, Inc. Records, 1968-2000s, Series 3:; (Box 1, 4, 5; 0.7 linear feet)
  Found here are records and items produced as part of Brown's First National Church of Exquisite Panic, Inc. Included are a certificate of incorporation, seal, various written manifestos and doctrines of the church, as well as signs, graphics, and ephemera used as part of the performances and public events. Also found are reproductions and documentation regarding Brown's series of artwork called "Anoter Map to Navada," created as part of his church's philosophies, as well as sheets of paper with "teachings" written in black marker.
  - "Another Map to Nevada" Series, 2000s (Box 1, Folder 18-19)
  - Book, Ikons of the First National Church of Exquisite Panic, Inc., circa 1992 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Certificate of Incorporation, 1968 (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Manifesto, Statements, and Doctrines, circa 1992 (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - Signs and Graphics, 1990s-2000s, (Oversized items housed in box 5, folder 1) (Box 1, Folder 23-24)
  - Stock Certificates, circa 1968 (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - Tax Document, 1986 (Box 1, Folder 26)
  - "Teachings", 2003 January 18 (Box 1, Folder 27)
  - "Teachings", circa 2000s (Box 1, Folder 28)
  - T-Shirt, circa 1990s (Box 4)
  - Corporate Seal, 1968 (Box 4)
  - Buttons and Stickers, circa 1990s (Box 4)
  - Oversized Signs and Graphics, 1990s-2000s, (Oversized items from box 1, folders 23-24) (Box 5, Folder 2)
- Printed Material, 1964-2008, Series 4:; (Box 1-2; 0.4 linear feet)
  Printed material primarily consists of books. Of note are books on Brown's "Collaborative Action Gluings" and "First Class Portraits," as well as a 1992 Fluxus event. Also found is an announcement for his 1964 "Meat Show" installation. One folder of miscellaneous printed material contains fliers, brochures, and exhibition announcements.
  - Announcement for "Meat Show", 1964 (Box 1, Folder 29)
  - Collaborative Action Gluings: Robert Delford Brown, 2004 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - First Class Portraits by Robert Delford Brown, 1973 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Flux-Flag, 1992 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Operating Manual for Spaceship Earth by R. Buckminster Fuller (Photocopy), 1971 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - A Pictographic History of the Oglala Sioux, 1967 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - RE/Search # 11: Pranks!, 1987 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Miscellaneous Printed Material, 1973, circa 2004-2008 (Box 2, Folder 7)
- Photographic Material, 1965-2009, Series 5:; (Box 2-3; 1.1 linear feet)
  The bulk of the photographs found here depict Brown's trips to Brazil and China. Also found are photographs labeled as depicting a collaborative art project with artist Victoria Schultz and others in Paris. Slides and digital photographs depict these same subjects as well as Brown's artwork. Also of note are black and white photographs of the interior of "The Great Building Crack-Up." Researchers should note that many additional photographs are included in Series 7: Scrapbook.
  - Robert Delford Brown, circa 2000s (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Brazil, 2003 (Box 2, Folder 9-17)
  - Brazil - Negatives, 2003 (Box 2, Folder 18-20)
  - Cats, 1965, 1980s-1990s (Box 2, Folder 21)
  - China, 2001 (Box 2, Folder 22-26)
  - China - Negatives, 2001 (Box 2, Folder 27)
  - "Collaboration with Victoria Schultz and two other women - Paris", circa 2004 (Box 3, Folder 1-3)
  - Events, 1990s-2000s (Box 3, Folder 4-8)
  - Great Building Crack-Up, circa 1970s (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - "Porto Allegre" Negatives and Slides, circa 2003 (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - Slides, circa 1980s-2000s (Box 3, Folder 11-16)
  - Digital Photographs, 1998-2009, (5 CD-Rs) (Box 3, Folder 17-18)
- Video Recordings of Performance Art, 1994-2005, Series 6:; (Box 3; 0.4 linear feet)
  Video recordings depict solo and collaborative performance art events created by Robert Delford Brown. Included is a recording of a solo performance art piece "Fried Blood." Three collaborative performance art events involved gathering the public, primarily children, to participate in activities such as pumpkin carving, balloon paintings, and creating a collaged environment out of paper.
  - Performance Art by Robert Delford Brown, "Fried Blood", 1994 May 27, (1 original videocassette: U-Matic, 1 duplicate videocassette: Betacam, 1 duplicate DVD) (Box 3, Folder 19-20)
  - Collaborative Performance Art (Box 3)
    - "Balloonatic Action Balloonary", 2005 March 3, (1 DVD and 1 duplicate DVD) (Box 3, Folder 21)
    - "Martian Outpost", 1998 April 14, (1 videocassette: Hi8, 1 duplicate videocassette: Betacam, 1 duplicate DVD) (Box 3, Folder 22-24)
    - "Pumpkin Carving", 2004, (1 DVD and 1 duplicate DVD) (Box 3, Folder 25)
- Scrapbook, 1964-1974, Series 7:; (Box 5; 4 folders)
  One large scrapbook contains documentation on Robert Delford Brown's art events, happenings, and environments from 1964 to 1974. A large portion of the scrapbook documents the "Meat Show" event that Brown created in 1964. Found here are photographs of the installation, press materials, and a list of supplies needed. Also included in the scrapbook are photographs depicting Brown working on projects, events, people such as Claes Oldenburg and Mario Amaya, and interior and exterior views of "The Great Building Crack-Up." Additionally, there are newspaper and magazine clippings, press releases, event announcements, scattered letters, and documentation on the founding of The First National Church of Exquisite Panic, Inc.
  Scrapbook materials have been removed from the original album and housed in archival folders. The original order of the documents has been maintained.
  - Scrapbook, 1964-1974 (Box 5, Folder 3-6)